Butler Metcalfe Houses Collection, 1979-1999
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Butler Metcalfe Houses Collection
1979 - 1999
Materials compiled during the restoration of the Butler mansion and Metcalfe house on North St. and Delaware Ave.
2 boxes (1.0 linear ft.)
Delaware North Companies
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
This collection is arranged and organized in two boxes. Box 1 contains clippings, articles, and related textual materials. Box 2 contains photographic material.
Researchers wishing to access this collection must apply for a Scholar Pass and present valid photo ID upon arrival to the library.
The Butler mansion was designed by architect Stanford White and built by the architectural firm McKim, Mead and White; construction began in 1896. Its first occupants were the George Williams family, who commissioned the home. In 1908, the mansion was purchased by Edward Butler Sr., founder of what is now known as The Buffalo News. The neighboring Metcalfe house was built in 1884 by McKim, Mead and White for Erzelia F. Metcalfe and her son James S. Metcalfe and was demolished in 1980.
De Long, David Gilson, 1939-; Harris, Susan J. H.; Johnson Bordes, Marilynn; Butler Mansion; Delaware North Companies; Lucas Varity Inc.; Metcalfe House; NorthWord; Legacy Project (National Trust for Historic Preservation in the United States); WNED-TV (Television station: Buffalo, N.Y.)
This collection consists chiefly of correspondence, photographs, negatives, slides, contact sheets, clippings, articles (including two longer book-length ones), guidelines for restoration, and related materials that were compiled during the restoration of the Butler Mansion on Delaware Avenue and North Steet in the 1980s. The collection also contains two folders of clippings on the Metcalfe House.
- Butler House/ Susan J. H. Harris, 1980
- Butler Mansion, Guidelines for interior alterations, 1980
- Butler Mansion history / R.L. H. pp 1 – 27 copy 1, 1997
- Butler Mansion history / R.L. H. pp 1 – 27 copy 2, 1997
- Butler Mansion, renovation
- Metcalfe House, 1979 - 1988
- Metcalfe House, 1989 - 1992
- Clippings, 1979
- Clippings, 1980
- Clippings, 1988 - 1999
- NorthWord article, 1988
- Buffalo News, 1989 - 1990
- Tour script and essay
- Tours, 1989
- National Historic Preservation Aware
- One Delaware North Place brochure, 1989
- Channel 17 documentary, 1989
- Lucas Varity brochure
- zack test, 1920
- Butler Mansion history / R.L. H. pp 1 – 51 +, 1997